hi this is Christian Dy from latitude west
financial i thought i would take this opportunity
to explain the changes that are happening with
the manulife disability insurance policy for the
dental students so things to consider about
the insurance so first question to answer
is why to get disability insurance for dentists
so dentists aren't covered through work uh they're
essentially self-employed business owners so it's
their responsibility to get the coverage on their
own so why should i get it in school when i'm not
working yet well there's three factors constantly
moving in the wrong direction one is your age one
is the rates and one is your health these are all
factors that might cause you to pay more for your
disability insurance uh or to potentially even be
declined from it um you you typically need this
insurance in order to work um and you know for
for multiple reasons so essentially everybody gets
this type of insurance in the same way they get
you know car insurance so a quick case study over
here so um i have a case study of susie and she
delayed her disability insurance and decided
to place it in fourth year so at graduation
because the foray was no longer available she
was then of course had to have to get a 3a policy
she had an exclusion on her right hand because
of a snowboard injury she also had a mental
health exclusion because she decided to do some
counseling while at ubc for stress and anxiety uh
and then she was rated to for a 200 percent
rating so what i'm doing is a case study as
to potentially what might happen of a standard
policy versus you know a rated policy so at
age 25 for 500 per month of coverage which is the
minimum amount of coverage but at a foray discount
with manulife um with that and the discount at 15
percent this policy is about 45 dollars per month
now if we fast forward uh when
suzy goes into her fourth year
and she's got of course the injuries and the
ratings and things of that sort and has now been
downgraded to a 3a and has lost her discount the
policy should have cost her about 163 per month
uh when she puts in the grad limit of 3 500 per
month of coverage but because of this you know
of the rating the loss of the discount plus
the 3a this policy is now as high as 339.
so this case study is is basically saying what
might happen by delaying so what are other ratings
and exclusions so a rating is when a percentage is
added on to your disability insurance because of
some sort of a pre-existing condition or some sort
of a health style risk an exclusion is when um
there's something in your something in your your
your lifestyle or something in your health which
they feel the insurance company feels is too high
of a risk so what they end up doing is they cause
it to be an exclusion so for example if you were
to you know be a diabetic or if you had mental
health issues then they can say here is your
disability insurance policy which we have approved
but it's excluded for mental health which means
if you uh had a a mental health history and you
were to claim a disability insurance from it then
uh it's just not covered so so travel is actually
another one uh if they it is possible that they
could exclude travel if you travel regularly to
uh what they might consider a red zone country so
they would say you're covered uh here in canada
north america and europe but if you were to
travel into one of these specific countries
uh then you um uh might be exclu then then then
it would not pay out the claim but we wouldn't
be able to determine this until you actually apply
because it's not just you know one one paint brush
it depends on a case by case scenario and any
sort of injuries with your knees joints um
these are all things that could affect a rating or
an exclusion when you're young it's the absolute
best time to put a policy in place send in
an application just to see uh what type of
rating or exclusions there are and the one of
the wonderful things that i'm able to help with
is if you potentially believe that you might have
a rating or an exclusion because i'm an elite
advisor i'm able to have a dedicated underwriter
that i can speak with i don't have to send an
email i don't have to fill out an application i
can just call them and talk to them about your
scenario without even mentioning your name just
to get a better understanding of what we might
do to improve your scenario or uh or what type of
rating or exclusion we might expect to see whether
it's worth it to even apply so that again is
one of the advantages that i'm able to help with
so what is the big change happening in september
so manulife uh which is essentially the best
policy for dental students will be canceling
their 4a disability plan called the pro-guard
series so what is the consequences of of
of this policy no longer being offered
so now we'd have to go to another insurance
carrier and the other insurance carriers are all
only giving dentists a 3a so um if you were to do
a side-by-side comparison between a 4 and a 3a we
know for sure that the 3a will cost more for the
same amount of coverage compared to a 40 so your
your premiums will go higher and remember those
premiums stay with you for the rest of your career
uh you the own occupation is
available on a manulife for a policy
and with this own occupation it protects your
occupation as a dentist so what that means is
let's pretend that you were had a microbi
undergrad let's pretend you became a dentist
and let's say you injured your hand such to the
extent that you can no longer practice dentistry
so now i want you to imagine that you
are a foray with an own occupation class
if you decided to work elsewhere um they would
still pay you your disability insurance for your
um uh for the amount that you were covered for so
let's say you had ten thousand a month of coverage
you were working as a dentist and you were to
suddenly be injured uh and then you would get
this 10 000 per month now let's say you decided
to you know be a a college professor a lab tech
a teacher um would you get both the disability
insurance income and the new income and the answer
that with own occupation you would without own
occupation you then fall into something they call
regular occupation what that means is that they
would look at something that you were reasonably
trained for and an occupation that you can you can
continue to work at such as you know a lab tech or
such as a high school teacher or something like
that so that they would stop paying you your 10
000 even if you didn't go to work but they said
well this person has the ability to go to work
um and so we're going to stop paying them so
that's why own occupation is an incredibly
important feature to have in all disability plans
for for people with higher income such as dentists
the other uh uh the other issue with going
from a 4a to a 3a is the limits go down so
what the limits are is as a dental student you
can put as little as 500 a month um coverage in
and but you're guaranteed you know a limit
of 20 000 so so what that means is that
usually in first year you would put in a minimum
of 500 a maximum of 1500 you can choose whether
you want to do the minimum or maximum when you're
in fourth year you could put a maximum of 3500
um of coverage even though you don't have
a job yet but then when you start working
the coverage goes up based off of income
so what that means is if your income goes
to let's say 200 000 maybe you qualify for
coverage of you know let's say 10 000 a month
so then do i have to do medicals to to to to uh i
get that increase and the answer is no one of the
beautiful things about this plan the the pro guard
series manulife plan is that it has a guaranteed
feature of increasing your insurance without any
evidence of medicals well what if i end up being
sick what if i become diabetic what if i have
this massive knee injury or a hand injury do
they look at any of those things when i upgrade my
insurance and the answer is no they do not which
is why it's so important to apply when you're
young even if it's a very very very uh minimal
amount of a policy it's incredibly important
to apply when you're to lock in the plan itself
and what about the cost of it does that go up
so let's say you were to put in a 1500 per month
coverage um and let's say this costs 50 per month
as an example it will always cost you 50 a month
for that 1500 a month of coverage that does not
go up throughout your entire lifetime the only
time it goes up is when you add more insurance so
let's say uh you're practicing and you decide to
add another layer of 3 000 per month that 3 000
per month will now cost it'll depend on what are
the rates and what is your age and what is your
gender at the time you increase it so let's just
pretend it costs another 100 per month then for
the rest of your working years you will now be
paying 50 for the first layer and 100 for the next
layer totaling 150 but do i get a discount because
i'm no longer a student and the answer is yes as
long as you sign up for the proguard plan before
it expires it comes with a 15 discount but that's
a 15 discount for the rest of your life including
on the extra amounts that you add on that's the
beautiful thing about the manulife proguard plan
you get the 4a you get the 15 discount for your
lifetime you get the additional fio called future
insurability option up to 20 000 you get the
own occupation you get those higher limits
so one of the advantages of using myself and
the latitude west team to put in your policy
is that we are manulife's elite advisor now
not everyone is an elite advisor and i at ubc
dentistry and the only elite advisor with manulife
to the best of my knowledge so by being an elite
um i am given a dedicated underwriter i
have priority on all of the policies i
issue and i have priority on all the applications
that i submit which means that there won't be
a risk of missing the deadline because they only
give you a certain amount of months in order to
place the policy even if you submit your policy in
september there is no guarantee that it will meet
the 4a deadline because there is a time limit uh
and there are delays that can occur from you know
getting an attending physician statement from a
doctor there there's all these different things
that might delay it such as you know a backlog
with their underwriters there won't be a backlog
because i have a dedicated underwriter with my
policy so those are one of the advantages of me
being an elite advisor uh i have been manulife's
um top living benefits advisor since 2017 in
british columbia so um you're you're in good hands
with myself and i have never had a problem uh
making a claim uh because i have such a large um
a large dental as you know a large client book
i have a big team that sort of process claims
very very quickly uh and we have never had a
claim not um issued that we have submitted
so how else are we different as a company
so not only do we do insurance but we also help
our clients with business planning we do a lot
of educational workshops we help our students to
find jobs if they want our help and then there's
the financial planning the investments um uh
incorporating uh a and my favorite as well is
you know i'm i'm a big educator on stocks and real
estate investment real estate i have clients who
buy commercial properties i have clients who
buy dental clinics i buy clients who start
uh dental clinic facilities with medical clinics
pharmacies all attached and so what i like to do
is i like to use them as an educational
resource to network with my other dentists
so that they can help to teach them i know a lot
of information that i'm able to give but they have
this valuable dental information because they've
already done it that's one of the reasons why
our company is a little bit different because
we support not only um you know as a starting
point the insurance but then it will graduate to
uh dental financial planning it'll graduate to
you know investment planning and these are all of
the different ways that we are able to help you so
our practice is based off of insurance investments
as well as financial advising consulting we have a
team and we have partnerships with with accounting
firms with legal firms if you were to do a dental
residency maybe an oral surgeon something
that's of that sort we also offer through our
partnerships with our accounting from free um free
tax filing while you're in your residency as well
so our partnerships with ubc dentistry have
been very very long the longest running one
compared to other companies at ubc currently so
we've had we've been in partnership ships with
them for over 10 years as a sponsor so we have a
large large large amount of dental students that
are now practicing that are still part of our
community and are still very very happy to help
we have a strong relationship with the dus
and that relationship will continue through
our sponsorships one of the things that we love to
do is we love to teach my background is actually
in education i taught at the college level um and
i like to to bring my clients um into my private
workshops and teach them about various different
topics and a lot of times get guest speakers
so this could be on dental business planning
tax strategies real estate investing i usually
will ask the students what it is that they
want to learn over here and then what i love
to do bring in guest speakers bring in some of
the top dentists in the lower mainland or uh uh
even through webinar we had a few from the us
come to talk about how their their journey of
starting a business the challenges today
the advice that they have for the younger
guys over here one of the exciting things i'm
going to do this year is i have a few of my
dental uh grads from several years ago who are
starting dental practices in the lower mainland
and i want them to come to talk about their
journey uh with the younger guys but remember
these are all private sessions these are for
clients only majority of the new graduating class
2023 became latitude west clients i've taught
them i've brought them into my private workshops
i've networked with them i've introduced them to
other dentists at different events such as the pdc
um and i can and i will continue to
do so with the next graduating class
as well so a new feature that we have on
our website latitude west on our latitude
west.ca website is that we have a section called
webinar replays and for our webinar replays
there's a section dedicated just for dentists
and in there we have years of these wonderful
wonderful workshops with our guest speakers
talking about how do i find my first dental job
you know how do i accelerate my wealth as a doctor
uh how do i grant how do i transition out of
dental school correctly and how do i structure my
first year practice as well as many many many more
topics um so so these are meant for our clients
so unfortunately if you were to visit the site
the majority of these are locked but once you
become a client we basically unlock it so you
could listen to this to support your education
you know as an added as an added value for us and
i will continue to do these webinars and continue
to to record them and put them on our website so
that all of our dental clients has access to them
uh we had one of our wonderful dental um grads
summarize all of their notes in a very very neat
format course per course you know unit per unit
they put all these together for the sole purpose
of supporting and helping their fellow classmates
over here so this is another feature that we would
love to share with you uh whether you're in first
year whether you're in second third or fourth year
over here we'd love to be able to share this with
you as um as a client of latitude west as well if
it can be used to help to support your learning
so with our social i we love to socialize we'd
love to introduce you to other um uh uh to other
clients and so we like to give sometimes
the events of browns and the other year
we rented out the entire earls in yale town and
what we did was it was a great opportunity for
people to mingle um we had we had dentists as old
as in their 60s there we had once as young as in
first year but it was just a great environment for
people to to talk i introduced many that many of
the senior dentists to the younger ones and and
essentially it was just a great networking event
so our latitude west team is here to help
you if you did want to put in place or to
set up a phone call with us so that we can
you know process or answer your questions
and then process an application if need be
um um the the manual life representative uh
i'm very very close with here in british
columbia and he had a few words to say
hi my name is daryl faulkner i am the director of
individual insurance sales for manulife financial
here in british columbia i have had the pleasure
of working with christian for about eight years
um christian is an elite advisor which means
he is top of the table uh of a producer with
manulife financial on the insurance side in 2018
he was actually top for volume for living benefit
sales in british columbia so that means he really
does know what he's talking about when it comes to
critical illness and disability his knowledge
base is absolutely phenomenal he has a great
grasp of not only living benefits but the life
insurance and the investment side of the business
if you were to place your
business place your trust with
anybody you can work with i would
definitely recommend christian his firm
so if you're ready to talk um you can book a
call with my assistant uh we can go over any
of your questions assistant latitude dash
west.ca i always make myself available for
all of my clients so you can text me at
604-202-9178 if you had a question for me
um and or if you just wanted
to set up a a time to talk
i hope that this has helped in explaining myself
my team as well as the changes happening with
the disability insurance all right i will
talk to you soon and great have a great year